Pierce, Anna E.; Papers ua902.008
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Anna E. Pierce Papers
1884-1983
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Pierce, Anna Eloise, 1866-1956
ua902.008
0.5 cubic ft. 2 Digital Files
Namesake of Pierce Hall, she served as Dean of Women from 1913-1933, supported the construction of dorms for women and aided the institutionalization of in loco parentis.
Biographical History
Anna Eloise Pierce was born on September 18, 1866 to Edmund Pierce and Susan H. Sloan, both of Worcester, NY. She was the second of three children living on a 40-acre farm. She graduated from Albany High School in 1881 and began teaching at the age of 15. On June 26, 1884, Pierce graduated from the NYS Normal School in Albany. With the help of her cousin, Dr. Andrew S. Draper (Superintendent of Schools), Pierce received an appointment as a relief teacher and secretary to President Waterbury. After a year and a quarter as the Preceptress of the Lisle Academy in Lisle, NY, Anna Pierce began a lifelong professional association with the New York State Normal School.
Anna Pierce began her career at the Normal School on July 23, 1886, when President Brubacher hired her as a secretary and substitute. One year later, she was appointed as Member of the Faculty (September 19, 1887), teaching mathematics from 1882-1892. She remained in that post until September of 1891 when she became Principal of the Primary Department of the Model School of the newly renamed New York State Normal College. She eventually became the Dean of Women at the Normal School from 1913-1933, and was affectionately known as "Dean Annie." As dean, Anna Pierce, was perhaps best remembered for her support of the construction of dorms for women, and for the institutionalization of in loco parentis as it referred to women students.
In the 1920s, Pierce and John Sayles encouraged the alumni, friends of the college and the student body to raise funds to build dormitories. Throughout the 1920s, Pierce corresponded with Abby Rockefeller, wife of John D. Rockefeller, Jr. for information about her study of housing conditions for young women in industry. As Dean of Women, Pierce wished "to improve housing conditions for the women students in State College.It is a fact that in nearly all such institutions the women are inadequately housed in approved private homes, in sorority and other student-managed houses, or in boarding halls under private management all of which facilities fail in many particulars to give the influence and training that we ought to provide for these young women so soon to be sent out as leaders." By 1935, Pierce Hall was opened. At the same time, Sayles Hall was under construction' realizing one of Pierce's long-term goals for the College. For Pierce, long-range housing was to instill a higher-level of sensibilities in the students. In 1920, President Brubacher awarded Pierce with an honorary degree of Master of Pedagogy from the New York State College for Teachers.
In 1928 she authored Deans and Advisors of Women and Girls, where she outlined some of the main responsibilities of college personnel who deal closely with female students. For example, she expressed the need for religious and moral training, appropriate dress and personal appearance, and proper behavior at social activities. These philosophies were also outlined in the College's student handbooks, penned primarily by Pierce and outlining the rules for chaperonage, dress, etc. Around the same time, Pierce developed an interest in the health of students. In 1925, while Chairman of the Health Committee of the National Association of deans of Women, she directed a survey of the student health service in the United States. In 1927, she prepared a catalog of Student Health Literature.
In 1941 Pierce Hall on Alumni Quad, originally called the Alumni Residence Hall was renamed for Dean Anna Pierce. She continued to serve the school even after her retirement as dean, becoming active in the College's Alumni Association, which controlled campus residence halls, president of the Half Century Club of the Alumni Association, and active member of the Benevolent Association. She died at age 91 on November 6, 1956.
Scope and Contents
Her papers include her autobiography/memoir, correspondence, lecture notes, publications, clippings, a sound recording, and a diary relating to her studies at the New York State Normal School at Albany and her appointment as a teacher, to her service as an officer in the Alumni Association, and especially to her campaign to provide campus housing for women. Also included are the texts of lectures given by Pierce on the importance of spiritual training for youth.
Arrangement of the Collection
This collection has no series.
Acquisition Information
All items in this collection were transferred to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives. Box 2 was donated by the University Alumni Association.
Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted.
Women's rights--1910-1920.; Women in higher education; In loco parentis; Digital Files; UAlbany Faculty & Alumni Papers; Pierce, Anna Eloise, 1866-1956; State College for Teachers (Albany, N.Y.)
- Civil War Readings Bibliography, Undated (Box 1 (Anna E. Pierce Papers), Folder 1)
- Clippings (Miscellaneous), 1921-1983 (Box 1 (Anna E. Pierce Papers), Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1884-1886; 1911; 1920-1928; 1933; 1950 (Box 1 (Anna E. Pierce Papers), Folder 3)
- Diary, 1935-1947 (Box 1 (Anna E. Pierce Papers), Folder 4)
- Memoir (typescript) and Family History (1776-1927), Undated; 1.78 MB (Box 1 (Anna E. Pierce Papers), Folder 5)
- "Reunion of the Graduates of the Albany Normal School, Albany High School", 1883 (Box 1 (Anna E. Pierce Papers), Folder 6)
- Family and Teaching Certificates, 1853; 1881; 1888; 1921; 1948 (Box 1 (Anna E. Pierce Papers), Folder 7)
- Catalog of Literature for Advisers of Young Women and Girls, compiled by Anna E. Pierce (Box 1 (Anna E. Pierce Papers), Folder 8)
- Deans and Advisors of Women and Girls, by Anna E. Pierce (Box 1 (Anna E. Pierce Papers), Folder 9)
- Draft Autobiography, donated by Kendall Birr and Kathlyn Andrews, Undated; 1.48 MB (Box 2 (Anna E. Pierce Papers), Folder 1)
- Notes for lectures given by Anna E. Pierce, 1901-1906 (Box 2 (Anna E. Pierce Papers), Folder 2)
- Note mentioning basque and skirt worn by Anna E. Pierce and 1884 commencement ceremony, 1934 June 23 (Box 2 (Anna E. Pierce Papers), Folder 3)
- Correspondence between Mrs. Roderick J. McIntosh and Anna E. Pierce regarding the Western Branch of the Alumni Association, 1921 April 11-15 (Box 2 (Anna E. Pierce Papers), Folder 4)
- Program - Tenth Anniversary of the State College Co-Op, established September 1920 (Dean Pierce), ca. 1930 (Box 2 (Anna E. Pierce Papers), Folder 5)
- Two letters in script to Anna Pierce from William S. Twichell (class of 1889), 1947 February 19; 1947 June 5 (Box 2 (Anna E. Pierce Papers), Folder 6)
- "Some specific reasons why NYS College needs a residence hall," letter by Anna E. Pierce, Undated (Box 2 (Anna E. Pierce Papers), Folder 7)
- Portrait of Anna E. Pierce, ca. 1926-1929 (Box 2 (Anna E. Pierce Papers), Folder 8)
- Writings - "Choice of Attitudes," drafts and notes (Box 2 (Anna E. Pierce Papers), Folder 9)
- Questions about Women leaders, Undated (Box 2 (Anna E. Pierce Papers), Folder 10)
- Writings - "Economic Relationships and Responsibilities", 1919 November 5 (Box 2 (Anna E. Pierce Papers), Folder 11)
- Writings - "The Problem of Social Leadership in Schools and Colleges and its Solution", Undated (Box 2 (Anna E. Pierce Papers), Folder 12)
- Writings -"By-Products", Undated (Box 2 (Anna E. Pierce Papers), Folder 13)
- "Choice of Chance, Which Shall Rule My Life," speech fiven to the College News, 1925 October 26 (Box 2 (Anna E. Pierce Papers), Folder 14)
- "Women's Position and Treatment," speech given at Hudson YWCA, 1917 September 10 (Box 2 (Anna E. Pierce Papers), Folder 15)
- "The Home-Maker's Responsibility for the Student's Success," speech given to Student Housing, 1917 November 22 (Box 2 (Anna E. Pierce Papers), Folder 16)
- Sound Recording, Souvenir 45 of Anna Pierce's Voice (Phonograph-record 1)